in this video I'm finally going to give
a definition of spinners using Clifford
algebras Spinners are members of minimal
left ideals in Clifford
algebras this definition is a bit
abstract but it works in any dimension
for both space and
SpaceTime we're going to see that the
2x1 column po Spinners we saw earlier in
the series can be incorporated into
Clifford algebras in the form of 2x two
matrices where only the First Column is
nonzero these special matrices belong to
a minimal left ideal as we learned in
the previous video These matrices form a
left ideal because when a matrix is
Multiplied onto them from the left the
result retains the same form of only the
First Column being
nonzero po Spinners are rotated using
single sided Transformations with half
angle su2 matrices which is equivalent
to the quatern I in Clifford algebras we
write the spinner rotation using a 2x2
matrix acted on by a half angle member
of the spin 3 Group which is equivalent
to the su2
matrices this single-sided
transformation is different than vectors
which transform with double-sided
Transformations with half angle su2
matrices or half angle members of the
spin 3 group if any of that seemed
confusing I'll explain it all step by
step in this
video let's start with a quick review of
Clifford algebras and their Matrix
representations the Clifford algebra
clpq is given by P basis vectors that
square to + 1 and Q basis vectors that
square to minus one the basis vectors
are orthogonal and so they anticommute
with each other so we can swap their
order in exchange for a negative sign
for example
cl30 has three basis vectors Sigma X
Sigma Y and sigma Z that all square to +
one and anti- commute with each other
this may be more familiar in the Matrix
representation which is given by the PO
or Sigma
matrices let's take a closer look at
cl30 which is built from the three basic
vectors Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z
but the Clifford algebra
cl30 itself is eight dimensional because
it contains one scaler three vectors
three bi vectors and one Tri Vector the
bi vectors are sometimes called pseudo
vectors because they can be thought of
as a rotation about an
axis the tri Vector is sometimes called
the pseudo scaler and is often written
as a capital I you can check for
yourself that the tri Vector squares to
-1 the tri Vector also commutes with
everything in the cl30 algebra and so
the order of multiplication with the tri
Vector doesn't
matter in this way the tri Vector in
cl30 is sort of like the complex I which
is normally written in lower case but
since we're really talking about a tri
Vector here we denote it with a capital
i the bi vectors are sometimes written
as a vector times the tri Vector like
this this is their pseudo Vector form
and it emphasizes that they can be
thought of as a rotation about a
particular
axis we can represent all abstract
symbols in
cl30 as 2x two
matrices the scaler one is the identity
Matrix the vectors are given by the
three po matrices and the rest can be
computed by doing the standard Matrix
multiplications the tri vector or pseudo
scaler is just the identity Matrix times
the complex I this gives us eight
matrices in total by adding these eight
matrices together in linear combination
we can get any 2x2 matrix with any
complex entries that we like by
specifying these eight real
coefficients now how do spinners fit in
here the Spinners associated with 3D
space are called po Spinners and as
we've seen in previous videos they are
written as 2x1 Columns of complex
numbers according to the star Garlock
experiment that deflects electrically
neutral particles in a magnetic field
according to their spin the top spinner
component is associated with the spin
Upstate plus Zed and the bottom spinner
component is assoc associated with the
spin down State minus Z but everything
in the Clifford algebra
cl30 is made of 2x two matrices so how
can we fit our 2x1 po Spinners inside of
our Clifford algebra the key to solving
this problem is either very smart or
very stupid depending on your point of
view all we do is take our 2x1 po
spinner and extend it with an extra
column of zeros so so that it becomes a
2x2 matrix this is how we write poy
Spinners inside the Clifford algebra
cl30 so our spin up state would be this
Matrix with a one in the upper left and
our spin down state would be this Matrix
with a one in the lower
left but how do we build these matrices
using the eight basis matrices in our
Clifford
algebra let's start with our plus Z spin
up
spinner just looking at the matrices it
looks like if we add 1 and sigma Zed
together we get the right answer if we
divide by two the lower right values
cancel and 1 + 1 becomes 2 and divided
by two becomes one so this is our spin
up
spinner for our minus Z spin down
spinner it looks like Sigma X and the
sigma y pseudo Vector give us the right
answer
if we subtract them and divide by two
indeed the upper right entries cancel
and 1 + 1 divided two gives us one so
this is our spin down
spinner note that we can rewrite the
sigma y pseudo Vector as the Z x by
vector and then swap Sigma Zed and sigma
x with a sign change then factor out
Sigma X this gives us Sigma x * the spin
spin up spinner and this is an
alternative way of writing the spin down
spinner so in quantum mechanics we
normally write a spinner as a linear
combination of the spin up and spin down
basis Spinners using components Cai 1
and Cai 2 but now we replace these basis
Spinners with these elements from our
cliford algebra which correspond to
these 2x two matrices here
and if we rotate this spinner using a
single-sided half angle su2 Matrix we
get the same result we would expect from
standard quantum mechanics just with an
extra column of zeros added
on in the language of Clifford algebras
we replace the su2 Matrix with an
equivalent spin 30 group member so now
we can rotate Spinners in purely
symbolic notation in our Clifford
algebra
as an exercise you can try checking that
this symbolic Clifford algebra
multiplication works out to the
equivalent Matrix
result now we were able to build these
Spinners in the Clifford algebra
cl30 by visual inspection we started
with the Matrix representation for our
Spinners then looked at the basis
matrices available to us in the algebra
and we were able to guess the correct
matrices we needed to build the
spinner if we forget about the matrices
and just use the symbols we have an
abstract version of our Spinners that
behaves the exact same
way this works fine in three dimensions
but how can we make this procedure work
in any
Dimension the key is to realize that
these special spinner matrices we used
are members of minimal left ideals in
Clifford algebras which is a definition
we covered in the last video spin
spinners for beginners number
13 if we add two spinner matrices
together we get another spinner Matrix
and if we multiply a spinner Matrix from
the left by any 2x two Matrix we get
another spinner
Matrix these two properties are the
definition of a left ideal we say it is
a left ideal because the multiplication
property only works if we multiply the
2x two matrices from the left if we
multiply a 2X two Matrix from the right
we don't get a spinner Matrix
back so we see that Spinners are members
of left ideals in Clifford
algebras but what is a minimal left
ideal we say an ideal set is minimal
when there are no sub ideals inside of
it ignoring the trivial ideal consisting
of just the zero element I actually
forgot to exclude the trivial zero ideal
in my definition in the last video so
keep in mind when I say minimal ideal I
mean the ideal has no sub ideals inside
of it except for the trivial zero
ideal this property of being minimal
doesn't come up with the 2x two matrices
so let's look at 4x4 matrices
instead the set of matrices here where
the first pair of columns are non zero
and the second pair of columns are zero
is a left ideal in the set of 4x4
matrices however it's not a minimal left
ideal there are actually smaller left
ideal sets found inside it the set where
only the First Column is nonzero and the
set where only the second column is
nonzero when we say Spinners are members
of minimal left ideals in Clifford
algebras we're basically saying that the
Matrix representation of the spinner
behaves like a matrix with a single
nonzero column now I want to be clear
that not all minimal left ideals look
like matrices with single non-zero
columns matrices that belong to minimal
left ideals are not always obvious at
first glance and we need to keep their
formal definition in mind however for
Simplicity we'll often use a matrix
where only the leftmost column is
nonzero because it's easier to
understand this lets us take the column
Spinners we've seen previously like Po
Spinners vile Spinners and dra Spinners
and write them using abstract symbols in
Clifford
algebras now we've seen how to build po
Spinners by using Matrix representations
first and then working backwards to the
abstract Clifford algebra symbols but
what if we want to build Spinners
without the Matrix
representations the key is to use the
projectors we learned about in the last
video remember a projector is an element
P that squares to
itself when a projector acts on an
algebra the result of the projection is
always un ideal for example when this
projector Matrix pz plus has a 2X two
Matrix multiplied onto it from the left
the result is a member of a left
ideal the same rule applies when we take
an abstract projector made of symbols
and apply our cliff algebra onto it from
the left we learned in the last video
that if we have a unit element U that
squares 2 + 1 then the expression 12 * 1
+ U is a projector because this
expression squares to
itself let's try making a projector made
with Sigma Zed and seeing what happens
when we multiply the algebra cl30 onto
it from the
left before we do I'll introduce one
helpful Pro ejector property from this
thesis by Crystal and McKenzie called
the poman property this thesis has a lot
of good information on building Spinners
using minimal left ideals in Clifford
algebras particularly in appendix B I've
left a link to this thesis in the
description in games like Pac-Man or Mrs
Pac-Man the character is often seen
eating up a line of pellets one by one
until there are none left
our projector pz plus behaves the same
way if we multiply it onto Sigma Zed and
then work out the multiplication the
sigma Zed effectively disappears just
like one of the pellets leaving us only
with the projector pz
plus so if we have the projector pz plus
put in front of a long trail of Sigma Zs
the projector can eat up the sigma Zeds
one by one until they all disappear
so we can get a pz plus projector to eat
up a line of Sigma Zeds or use the
property in Reverse to create a line of
Sigma Zeds in front of the
projector this property works on both
the left and right sides of the
projector with the poman property in
mind let's take our eight basis elements
from the Clifford algebra
cl30 and multiply them onto our
projector pz Plus
multiplying the projector with one just
gives us our projector back multiplying
the projector with Sigma X we distribute
and get this for convenience I'm going
to rewrite this B Vector Sigma x * Sigma
Z in its pseudo Vector form asga Sigma y
* the pseudo scalar capital
I multiplying the projector with Sigma Y
and distributing I will again rewrite
the by Vector Sigma y * Sigma Z in
pseudo Vector form as Sigma x *
I multiplying the projector with Sigma
Zed just gives us the projector back by
the poman property notice that this is
the same result as just multiplying the
projector with
one with Sigma y Sigma Zed this actually
gives us the same result as just Sigma y
remember the poman property allows us to
use this projector to eat up Sigma Zed
and ignore it with Sigma Z * Sigma X we
can swap the order and pick up a
negative sign and ignoring Sigma Zed
using the poman property we get the same
result as Sigma X but with a minus sign
in
front multiplying with Sigma x * Sigma Y
and distributing I can rewrite this B
Vector as a pseudo vector and just
rewrite the tri Vector as the
pseudoscalar capital i
multiplying with the tri Vector gives us
the same result since we can just ignore
the sigma Zed by the paman
property so when we take the eight basis
elements of
cl30 and then put them through a
projector with pz plus we only get four
independent elements out on the other
side in one case we get plus and minus
versions of the same element but these
are not independent since we can go from
one to the other through scalar
multiplication by
-1 it makes sense that we turned eight
elements into four elements because the
projector operation essentially lets us
forget about the sigma Zeds in our
formulas so any basis elements that only
differ by a factor of Sigma Zed get
projected to the same
result so these four elements form a
basis of our minimal left ideal in
cl30 I can re write these elements AS pz
Plus Sigma X pz plus I Sigma X pz Plus
and I pz
plus if we write out the Matrix
representations of these Spinners we
find they correspond to the four
different real numbers inside a 2x1 PO
column spinner they are just written in
abstract form
instead we can alternatively think of
this as two basis vectors with complex
coefficients in front if we allow the
pseudoscalar I to instead be represented
by the complex
I here pz plus represents the spin
Upstate and sigma X pz Plus represents
the spin down
state now I would like to take this
minimal left ideal definition of
spinners and generalize it to any
Dimension but first i'm going to spend a
little more time thinking about Spinners
in cl3 3 and make sure they're exactly
the objects we want for quantum
mechanics one thing to check is to make
sure Spinners behave properly when we
act on them with Quantum
operators in the staran Garlock
experiment there are two possible
measurements spin up or spin down we
denote these measurements by plus h/2
andus
h/2 algebraically these are measured by
applying the spin Z operator onto our
spin States this operator equals h/2 *
Sigma Z so let's see what happens when
we take our spin States and operate on
them with Sigma Zed if we apply Sigma
Zed to our spin up State this is the
same thing as applying Sigma Zed to our
pz plus projector so it gets eaten up by
the poman property giving back just our
spin up state so the spin Zed up
operator measures Plus h/2 on the spin
up State as
expected we can also apply Sigma Zed to
our spin down state which we can write
as Sigma x * P
z+ swapping the two sigmas gives us a
negative sign and the pz plus projector
eats up the sigma Zed leaving us with
the negative of our spin down state so
the spin Zed operator measures minus h
over2 on the spin down state as
expected so we can see that our Clifford
algebra Spinners obey the standard rules
of quantum
mechanics we can also build the plus x -
X Plus Y and minus y States out of our
plus Z and minus Z States and the
corresponding operators behave as
expected something else to consider are
dual
Spinners in quantum mechanics we often
deal with spinners also called CET
Spinners as well as dual Spinners also
called bra Spinners put together a bra
and K or bracket output a scalar complex
number which is the probability
amplitude of one state collapsing onto
the other normally we think of bras as
being the hermiss conjugate of kets
denoted with a dagger in other words we
take a KET column and transpose it into
a row and take the complex conjugate of
the entries
if we take the hermiss conjugate of one
of our 2x two spinner matrices where
only the First Column is non zero we end
up with a 2x2 matrix where only the
first row is non zero this is a minimal
right ideal of
cl30 so Spinners live in minimal left
ideals and dual Spinners live in minimal
right
ideals remember we get a left ideal by
multiplying 2x two matrices onto our
projector from the the left and we get a
right ideal by multiplying 2x two
matrices onto our projector from the
right when using the abstract symbols of
Clifford algebras the dagger operation
no longer means Herm Mission conjugate
instead it indicates the reversal
operation so if we have a general multiv
Vector M multiplied onto the projector
from the left and we take the reverse of
this we end up with the reverse of the
projector times the reverse of the
multiv vector and since our projector is
only made up of a scaler plus a vector
the reverse operation does nothing to
it so essentially the reverse operator
switches us from a left ideal to a right
ideal in other words the reverse
operator changes a spinner into a dual
spinner so if we take a spinner Cai
written as a linear combination of spin
up and spin down States and then take
its reverse reverse this applies the
reverse to the components and the basis
Spinners and exchanges their order the
reverse also changes the basis Spinners
into dual basis
Spinners it's also worth noting that our
spinner components are actually a sum of
a scaler and a tri vector or pseudo
scaler when we take the reverse of this
the scaler one is unchanged but the
Reversed pseudo scaler gets an extra
minus sign so so here the reverse
operator is playing a role similar to
The Complex
conjugate also recall that both scalers
and sud sudo scalers commute with
everything in the algebra so we can move
them to the left or right of basis
spinners for
free now let's try performing the inner
product between a bra and a KET if we do
this using our 2x two matrices we
unfortunately don't get a scaler we get
the inner product result in the top left
entry of the The Matrix but a true
scaler in a Clifford algebra would be
this number multiplied by the scaler one
which is the identity Matrix how can we
fix this we get around this problem by
using something called the grade
projection operator denoted with angle
brackets and a subscript K this operator
takes a multiv vector as input and
outputs the Ki grade elements inside the
multiv vector for example given a multiv
Vector M the grade zero projection gives
us the scalar part the grade 1
projection gives us the vector part the
grade two projection gives us the bi
Vector part and the grade three
projection gives us the tri Vector part
the result of our dual spinner acting on
a spinner is this expression times our
pz plus operator which has a scalar part
plus a vector part to get the scalar
part on its own all we do is use the
grade projection operator and then we
multiply by two to get rid of the factor
of
1/2 note that many sources will omit the
zero subscript in the special case of a
grade zero projection as a convention in
their
notation so in
cl30 we calculate the inner product of
two spinners Zeta and Cai by taking the
Clifford product of Zeta reverse and Kai
and projecting out the scalar part and
multiplying by
two here the kai acts like a cat spinner
from a minimal left ideal and The Zeta
reverse acts like a bra spinner or dual
spinner from a minimal right
ideal another thing to check is to make
sure that a spinner and a dual spinner
multiply together in the other direction
to give a vector in previous videos I
talked about how Spinners are sort of
like the square roots of vectors because
we can factor a POI vector into a
spinner times a dual spinner we should
also check that we can multiply a
spinner and dual spinner into a vector
in Clifford
algebras note that the cat spinner has
components Cai 1 and Cai 2 and the bra
dual spinner has components negative 2
and Cai
1 we can write out these Spinners as
linear combinations of our plus Z and
minus Z basis Spinners we can then
rewrite the plus Z spinner as our pz
plus projector and rewrite the minus Z
spinner as Sigma x * P
z+ we can factor out pz Plus on the
right of the first term and factor out
pz plus from the left side of the second
term because pz plus is a projector its
square equals itself we can now rewrite
pz plus as 1 12 * 1 + Sigma Z
Distributing this product of three sums
gives gives us eight terms in total we
can do some simplifications here for
example Sigma x^2 goes to 1 and we can
flip the order of the sigmas here if we
change the sign and flip the sigmas here
if we also change the sign and set Sigma
x^2 to 1 also note that the plus and
minus versions of these terms cancel and
go to
zero we can then group the six remaining
terms into Sigma X Sigma Z * Sigma X and
sigma Z next I'll distribute the 1/2 and
I'm going to rewrite the Z x by Vector
in pseudo Vector form as I * Sigma
y if we set these terms equal to 3D
Vector components XY Z and also change
the tri Vector big I to the complex
small I we get the exact formulas for
converting between 3D Vector components
and complex spinner compon components
that I showed in spinners for beginners
video
7 so in the Clifford algebra
cl30 we can successfully factor a 3D
Vector into a pair of spinners as
expected we just have to keep in mind
that the components of this 3D Vector
include both scalar parts and
pseudoscalar
parts now in this video series I've
defined Spinners as members of minimal
left ideals in Clifford
algebras however I mentioned in a
previous video that David Honis one of
the leading figures in geometric algebra
defines Spinners as any sum of even
graded elements in a Clifford algebra so
why are these two definitions
different the link between these two
definitions is the poman property recall
we can get a left ideal inside our
Clifford algebra by applying the algebra
onto a projector pz plus from the left
left the projection operation squashes
our eight-dimensional space into a
four-dimensional space in doing so it
makes it so that we can no longer tell
the difference between elements if they
differ by a factor of Sigma Zed for
example we can no longer tell the
difference between Sigma Y and sigma y *
Sigma Z because our pz plus projector
eats up the sigma Zed making it
disappear this means that that when we
have a big Clifford algebra expression
like this that is projected using pz
plus we can feel free to add or remove
Sigma Zeds as we
please this means that we have the power
to make every term in this expression
have an even grade for example the
scalar one has grade zero so we leave it
alone the vectors Sigma X and sigma y
are grade one so we can multiply them by
an extra Sigma Zed to make them grade
two for the vector Sigma Zed we can
remove a factor of Sigma Zed just to get
a scalar one which is grade
zero all the B vectors are grade two so
we leave them alone and the tri Vector
is grade three but we can remove a
factor of Sigma Zed to make it grade
two so by adding and removing Sigma Zeds
as needed we have forced every element
in this expression to have an even grade
and this is completely equal to our
original spinner
formula all David Honis does for his
definition of spinners is simply drop
the projection from the right hand side
of this expression this even graded
element behaves exactly like the PO
Spinners we've seen all along it simply
doesn't care about the fact that the
second column of this Matrix is nonzero
since we only care about the First
Column anyway if we want to take this
Honis Style spinner and recover our
minimal left ideal spinner all we need
to do is apply it to our projection
operator from the
left so these two definitions of
spinners aren't exactly equal but they
are pretty close the only difference
between them is whether or not we do a
projection operator on the
right now let's take what we have for
Spinners in
cl30 and generalize it to SpaceTime with
cl13 and then generalize it further to
clpq in the SpaceTime algebra
cl13 gamma T squares 2 + 1 and gamma's
XY Z Square to minus1 and all basis
vectors anti-c commute with each other
in total There are 16 independent
elements in this Clifford algebra one
scaler four vectors Six B vectors four
Tri vectors and one quad Vector the quad
Vector at the top is also sometimes
called the pseudo scaler denoted with a
capital I and big I squares
to1 however this time big I anti-
commutes with vectors inside the algebra
so be careful about the ordering when
writing out multiplications that involve
big
I there are two popular Matrix
representations for
cl13 which are the chyal basis or vile
basis and and the mass basis or direct
basis as before the first thing we need
to get Spinners in a minimal left ideal
is a projector element recall that any
element of the form 12 * 1 + U where U ^
S 2 + 1 is a projector its complement 1
minus the projector is also a
projector in cl13 you might be tempted
to reach for a projector like pt+ which
is 1 12 * 1 + gamma T however when
looking at the Matrix representation of
this projector we find it can be written
as a sum of two projectors so this
projector is not a minimal projector
meaning it will not give us a minimal
left ideal indeed when we multiply a
general 4x4 Matrix onto it from the left
we get two nonzero columns instead of
just
one one solution is to take the result
of our projection and put it through yet
another projector to get an even smaller
ideal the term I gamma X gamma y squares
2 + 1 so this can give us another
projector pxy
+ note that this is the complex number I
from the set of scalers used in linear
combinations this is not the
pseudoscalar big I from our Clifford
algebra so we're actually making an
assumption here where we're allowed to
scale our Clifford algebra elements
using complex numbers so we'll add the
complex C here to denote this this is
different than what we were doing
previously in
cl30 where we were only using real
number scaling
coefficients it turns out that if we
project with pt+ and then project with
pxy + we get a minimal projector
p++ and this projects out the minimal
left ideal consisting of the first
nonzero column in The Matrix
representation also the existence of
this projector explains why PT Plus is
not minimal we can multiply PT Plus by 1
and then rewrite one as a sum of
complementary projectors pxy + and pxy
minus this gives us two projectors that
add up to pt+ proving that that pt+ is
not a minimal
projector in fact the different
combinations of pt+ PT minus pxy + and
pxy minus give us four different minimal
projectors that all sum to one or the
identity
Matrix however we're just going to go
with the first option since it's the
simplest a member of this minimal left
ideal is a set of four complex numbers
arranged in a column called a direct
spinner which we talked about in
spinners for beginners number nine so
this is the Matrix representation of a
direct spinner but what does it look
like in terms of abstract Clifford
algebra
symbols well each of our projectors has
its own poman property PT Plus will eat
up factors of gamma T and pxy plus will
eat up factors of gamma x * gamma y
possibly with a complex I or negative
sign left over depending on the swap
order and coefficients in
front however the most important
property here is that gamma t commutes
with I gamma X gamma y as a result our
projectors pt+ and pxy plus also commute
so we can change their order at any
time this means we can use PT Plus to
eat up factors of gamma T then swap the
projector order to eat up factors of
gamma X gamma Y and then swap back so
the order we multiply projectors in
doesn't matter we get to use two paman
properties at the same time for
free this means that when we project our
algebra using
p++ the elements one the T Vector the XY
by vector and the txy tri Vector are all
equivalent allowing for different
complex number scalings in
front the other equivalences are given
here so in the end we only have four
independent basis Vector elements in our
minimal left ideal The Matrix
representations for these basis elements
are given here you can see that we get
four basis elements for the four complex
entries in the First Column of our
Matrix there's also a way to subdivide a
directa spinner into a left chyro vial
spinner and a right chyro vial spinner
this is done with these two projectors
involving the complex small I times the
pseudoscalar big I a combination which
is sometimes written as gamma 5 for
short however note that the direct
spinner is Multiplied onto these
projectors from the right so these do
not belong to smaller left ideals inside
our minimal left ideal
I'll talk more about left and right
chyro vial Spinners in later
videos so we see that direct Spinners
are members of minimal left ideals in
Clifford algebra's
cl13 how can we generalize this to
clpq the main question is how do we find
a minimal projector that will give us a
minimal left ideal in a Clifford algebra
of arbitrary
size this is addressed in a textbook by
Lun
esto it turns out to be pretty easy if
we just follow the pattern established
in
cl13 if one projector isn't enough to
give us a minimal ideal we just keep
multiplying more projectors that commute
with it until we get a minimal
projector let's say we're working in the
Clifford algebra
cl80 with complex coefficients we have
these eight basis vectors that square 2
+ 1 one we can collect these basis
vectors into bi Vector pairs since the
bi vectors have no elements in common
all the bi vectors commute with each
other you can feel free to check this
for
yourself however each of these B vectors
squares 2 minus one which is not useful
for making
projectors so we include a scaling
factor of the complex I in front of each
B Vector which causes all the B vectors
to now sare 2 +
1 we can now use these bi vectors to
construct commuting projectors using the
formula 12 * 1 + U where U is our B
Vector time the complex I which squares
to +
1 by multiplying all these commuting
projectors together we get a minimal
projector which can be used to construct
a minimal left
ideal so for a Clifford algebra built
from an even number of basis vectors
getting a minimal projector is easy we
just group the basis vectors into
non-overlapping pairs to make a set of
commuting projectors and multiply all
the projectors
together but what if we have an odd
number of basis vectors it turns out the
final odd basis Vector will also commute
with all other bi vectors as long as no
basis vectors are repeated between the
bi vectors
the final basis Vector also squares 2 +
1 so it can be used to build a final
commuting projector so for Clifford
algebras with an odd number of basis
vectors we use the same procedure as the
even case but use the final odd basis
Vector to make our final commuting
projector now what about
clpq where some basis vectors Square 2
minus1 in this case the procedure for
building minimal projectors is the exact
same except some B vectors will Square
to + one all on their own so we don't
need to include a factor of the complex
I in
front we just include or exclude the
complex I as needed to ensure the B
Vector squares to +
one and we use our set of commuting
projectors to build our minimal
projector in the same
way now this procedure does leave some
questions first of all how do we know
for sure that projectors made from B
vectors give us a minimal left ideal
with no smaller non-trivial ideals
inside also what if we aren't allowed to
use complex coefficients as in the case
of cl30 with real
coefficients how do we know when we've
managed to build a minimal
projector unfortunately I'm going to
have to delay the proofs of this to an
appendix video
as this video is already too
long one last thing I'll mention is that
when building Matrix representations of
Clifford algebras you should make sure
the matrices you use are big enough to
hold the algebra for example cl30 with
real coefficients is eight real
dimensional and the 2x two matrices of
complex numbers is also eight real
dimensional so you can create a one
toone correspondence between the two
but cl30 with complex coefficients is 16
real dimensional and so the 2x2 complex
matrices are not big enough to hold it
if you try to use the standard Sigma
matrices you'll end up in a situation
where two different elements from the
Clifford algebra end up being
represented by the same
Matrix a matrix representation like this
is said to be not faithful we need to
increase the size of our matrices to
ensure we get faithful representations
with a one toone correspondence between
Clifford algebra elements and
matrices